"Randomized Controlled Trials of Taurine
Supplementation in Humans"
We know taurine abundance
decreases during aging,
and a reversal
of this decline
through taurine supplementation
increases the healthspan
and lifespan
in mice and worms,
and health in monkeys.
So, this means
taurine deficiency
is a driver of aging
in these species.
To test
whether taurine deficiency
is a driver of aging
in humans too,
long-term, well-controlled
taurine supplementation trials
that measure human
healthspan and lifespan
as outcomes are required.
Why haven't
these happened already?
You know why.
As a naturally
occurring substance,
taurine cannot be exploited
through a commercial patent.
You can buy pure taurine powder,
literally by the bucket,
at hardly a penny per gram.
So, who's going
to fund studies on it?
In population studies,
higher blood taurine levels
are associated with less obesity
and a lower prevalence
of type 2 diabetes,
but, when put to test,
as reviewed in
this 2020 meta-analysis
of randomized controlled trials,
taurine supplementation
had no significant effect
on blood sugar control,
LDL cholesterol,
or body weight,
though it did
drop blood pressures
and triglycerides a few points,
at a daily dose of
half a gram to six grams a day
between 15 days and 6 months.
A 2024 systematic review
and meta-analysis
of randomized controlled trials
found the same
small blood pressure
and triglycerides benefit,
as well as a small,
six-point drop
in fasting blood sugars...
though none of those few trials
on people with diabetes
showed that
blood pressure benefit,
though it did help
their blood sugars.
Taurine can also slow
our heart rate
by three or four
beats per minute,
which is considered
a good thing,
and, in addition
to lowering blood pressures,
it can improve
heart muscle function
in patients with heart failure.
What about artery function?
People with type 1 diabetes
were given
500 milligrams of taurine
three times a day for two weeks,
and researchers saw a
significant improvement
in their artery function.
As you can see,
those with type 1 diabetes
start out
with reduced artery function
compared to healthy controls,
and giving them a placebo
doesn't seem to help.
But the taurine
seemed to elevate
their artery function
closer to healthy levels.
What about
improving artery function
in people without diabetes?
In this study of individuals
with prehypertension,
about 130 over 80,
who took about the same amount,
1.6 grams a day for 12 weeks,
they got the same
blood pressure benefit
seen in the other trials
and, importantly,
improvement in artery function
compared to placebo.
What about effects on
inflammation and oxidation?
Taurine can decrease the levels
of c-reactive protein,
a marker of oxidative stress,
though it doesn't appear
to have much effect
on some other markers
of inflammation.
So, okay, some modest effects,
but there is
a substantial mismatch
between the strong
scientific foundation
supportive
of the health benefits
of taurine
in animal studies,
and the quality
of clinical trials
and their outcomes
in assessing the efficacy
of taurine in human health.
What's the harm
in taking it, though?
It's cheap and easy to find.
A one-gram dose would cost
as little as a penny a day.
Most Americans are getting
about 150 milligrams a day
in their diet,
mostly from meat.
We make taurine ourselves,
and so do many
of the animals we eat.
In fact,
our realization
that we made so much on our own
came from studies of vegans
who had taurine levels
that were not
significantly different
than those eating meat,
though they were
about 15 percent lower.
A subsequent study found
the taurine levels of vegans
were more like 20 percent
lower than meat eaters,
which did reach
statistical significance.
The clinical implications
of reduced blood taurine levels
in vegans are not known.
Our ability to make taurine
is supported by the fact
that taurine deficiency
has never been found
in vegetarians,
but just because
vegan levels aren't deficient
doesn't mean they are
necessarily optimal.
Taurine is considered
nonessential in adults
because it can be
readily synthesized
within our own bodies,
though infants may need
to get it in breast milk
until they can ramp up
their own synthesis.
But can adults make enough
for optimal health,
especially as we get older
and all our levels decline?
Why do our levels
even decline as we age?
It's not just because
we may be getting
less in our diet,
since if you get
none in your diet,
your levels may only be
about 20 percent lower
but levels over a lifespan
decline by about 80 percent,
suggesting we lose some
of our capacity to churn it out.
Taurine has been envisioned
as a longevity vitamin,
meaning it isn't like
an actual vitamin-vitamin,
where we die
if we don't get enough.
But even though we make it,
we may also need
to get some in our diet
to optimize metabolism.
In a review of what clinicians
might want to discuss
with their patients
on a plant-based diet
who are suffering
from some kind of problem,
are these conditionally
essential nutrients,
where,
under normal conditions,
they can be produced
in our own body
in sufficient amounts,
but something may interfere
with synthesis,
or conditions may arise
where we may need more.
Taurine is included
in this list,
as is carnitine,
another compound
found in meat
that we can make on our own.
But imagine if people
started taking
carnitine supplements,
thinking, "Why not,
what harm can it do?"
Of course, we now know
that carnitine
is one of the things
we try to avoid in meat,
because it turns into TMAO,
and may increase
the risk of heart disease,
kidney disease, and many
of our leading killers.
Indeed, if you give people
carnitine supplements,
their TMAO levels shoot up.
So, might that be
a precautionary tale
when it comes to taurine?
Take arginine, for example.
It's another non-essential
amino acid in adults
that has a variety of functions
other than being
part of proteins,
including delaying
the aging senescence
of arterial lining cells.
Animal studies have shown
all sorts
of heart healthy benefits
of arginine supplementation,
including
improved artery function
and inhibition
of atherosclerotic plaque,
just like taurine.
So, reviews like
these suggest studies
strongly support favorable
cardiovascular effects
accruing from L-arginine
supplementation
based on short-term studies,
just like taurine.
But long-term treatment
with arginine
actually accelerates
the aging process
in human artery lining cells.
Did this paradoxical effect
cause any actual problems?
Short-term supplementation
showed an improvement
in artery function.
In contrast,
long-term therapy
with arginine supplementation
did not improve artery
or heart function.
Instead, it led
to premature death.